Guide to the Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve records
1954-1992
SC0619
Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve (Calif.)
9 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Box 4 is restricted
Access Terms
Grundmann, Alan.; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Administration.;; Thomas, John Hunter.; Biological stations--California--Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve.; Searsville Lake (Calif.)
Collection Contents
- Records, Accesion ARCH-1997-198
  - Clippings, 1973-86 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Control Brush Burning pamphlet 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1974-76 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1977-89 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Courses at Jasper Ridge, 1977, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Crittenden, Mabel and Alan Grundmann, “Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve,” 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Discussion paper on Jasper Ridge (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Docent Days at Jasper Ridge, Spring 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Docent readings, winter quarter, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Docent Training Courses, syllabi and notes, 1983-85 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fire Management Demonstration, July 27, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Geology and Biology of Serpentine Soils, Biology 178 papers, Spring 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Grasses at Jasper Ridge, list, 1983; and “Some Grass Facts (and Rumors)” 1982-83 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Grundmann, Alan, “Present Thinking about Searsville Planning Questions,” March 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Guide for Tour Guides, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - A guide to Jasper Ridge; prepared by the students of Biology 178, Spring 1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Harvey, Alan and Richard Jeffers, “The Amphibians and Reptiles of Jasper Ridge,” Biology 199, June 1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Holm, Dick, “Report on Searsville Lake,” ca. 1971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Important Jasper Ridge historical dates, list of, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Improvements, update to Jasper Ridge Committee, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Introductory Training of Jasper Ridge Docents, Winter Quarter 1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Introductory Training to Jasper Ridge Docents, Spring Quarter 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Inventory of JRBP – Experimental Ecological Reserves, ca. 1975 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Jasper Ridge / San Francisquito Creek Waterways Paper (Alan Grundmann), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Jasper Ridge and the Man and the Biosphere Program, memo from Nona Chiariello with supporting documents, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve Management and Major Research Facility Requirements: 1975 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve, A University policy statement concerning academic program, community use, management, and financing. March-June 1974 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Jasper Ridge Committee minutes, March 8, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Jasper Ridge publications, theses, and dissertations (lists of), 1969-89 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Jasper Ridge tour, March 11, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Jasper Ridge: History of Public Exclusion (concerns closing off horse trails) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - JRBP book [Jasper Ridge: A Stanford Sanctuary] – emails regarding research, drafts for several chapters, and a brochure on the book (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - JRBP fence bids, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - JRBP flyers and notices, 1983-92 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - JRBP publications: Common Plants, Common Birds, Jasper Ridge Biological Experimental Area, Views from the Ridge (Spring 1984), Views Fall 1992, Wildflower calendar 1985, Jasper Ridge: Stanford’s Biological Preserve, and The Searsville Site Guide (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Layport, Cindy, “Assembling a Vertebrate Collection,” ARLO project, Spring 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Memoranda, 1970-72
    - Subjects include silting along Corte Madera Creek, research projects, and visit by Bechtel. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Memoranda, mostly by Alan Grundmann, 1973 Jan. - April
    - Subjects include funding issues, Trustee designation of JRBP, Shack Riders and horse trail issues, neighbor relations, chaparral control, camping request, and development. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Memoranda, mostly by Alan Grundmann, 1973 May – August
    - Subjects include Shack Riders and horse trail issues, Jasper Ridge incursions, development plan, zoning, funding issues, cattle on Jasper Ridge, Bechtel visit, and fencing issues. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Memoranda, mostly by Alan Grundmann, 1974
    - Subjects include management plan, Swamp trail problems, horse trail problems, chimp food garden, tours, fire road, signs, Searsville bomb threat, and fencing. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Memoranda, mostly by Alan Grundmann, 1975
    - Subjects include docent training, use of motor vehicles, mosquito abatement, insecticide use, office space, NSF facilities proposal, and boundary with SLAC. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Memoranda, mostly by Alan Grundmann, 1976
    - Subjects include research visits, docents, steelhead ladder at Lagunita Dam, mosquito abatement, office space, Lawrence Hall, Jasper Ridge Policy Committee, Searsville Lake swimming use, preserve boundaries, and buffer zone planting. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Memoranda, mostly by Alan Grundmann, 1977-79
    - Subjects include JRBP emblem, planning (includes draft of future goals), mosquito project, state park research possibilities, equipment, milfoil, fence plantings and boundary with SOPF. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Memoranda, mostly by Alan Grundmann, 1982-85
    - Subjects include scattering ashes at JRBP, camping, parking JR truck, regulations for conduct, funding, docent training, proposal for lysimeters, diversity enhancement, and fire road. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Memoranda, mostly by Alan Grundmann, 1986-92
    - Subjects include JR vegetation map and SLAC biological survey of San Francisquito Creek. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Mendell, Edward - tree-pruning case, 1982-86 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Mill, Ted, “Photooxidizing Properties of Searsville Lake,” presented at annual Jasper Ridge Seminar, Feb. 1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous materials (includes maps, fact sheets on JR birds, short descriptive pieces on JR) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Morell property, memos re, 1972-73 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Nishimoto, Judy, “The Social History of the Jasper Ridge Area (summary of a lecture give by Mrs. Dorothy Regnery)”, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notes on Trifolium by Herb Dengler (photocopy) 1982 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Permit renewal letter, 1985, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Plant and lichen lists 1988 and undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Policy Statement and Management Program for the Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve, Dept. of Biological Sciences, Spring 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Proposal for Jasper Ridge Bird Committee, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Proposed botany preserve maps (photocopies) 1923 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Reprints on JRBP: (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - A Request for the Addition of Area 8 and Parts of Area 4B of the Stanford Lands to the Academic Reserve of the University, submitted by the Dept. of Biological Sciences, October 23, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Research permits issued to persons not affiliated with Stanford University since circa 1975, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Research proposals 1984-1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - School Use of Searsville Lands, draft guidelines, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Searsville Lake Leasehold vis-à-vis the Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve, draft for a University Position Paper, October 1976 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Searsville Lake water memos, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Searsville Lands: teaching stations, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Searsville Park Exploratory Meeting with Ad Janes, Agenda, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Searsville Project Guidelines (Jasper Ridge Visitor Facilities), 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Seasonality on Jasper Ridge, Biology 178 papers, Spring 1975 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Shack Riders 1970-74 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Sign: closure of Searsville Park, summer 1977 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Sims Memorial Fund, memos and correspondence, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Speech notes (possibly those John Thomas) (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Tentative Proposal to the NSF on behalf of the Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve, general draft #1, May 1979 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Thomas, John “Appendix I” – list of Jasper Ridge papers, conduct regulation, cost calculation, and CV for 5 professors, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Thomas, John, “The Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve Teaching and Reference Collection of Vascular Plants,” 1992 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Thomas, John, miscellaneous correspondence, 1959-61 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Thomas, John– vita (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Topics in Ecology, Biology 178 papers, Spring 1973 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Tree nursery lease, memos, etc., 1974 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Trespass law, memos, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Wessells, Norm, draft of memo on management plan and letter about association of JRBP with UC Natural Land and Water Reserves Sytem, ca. 1973 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - White, Ray, “Geology of Jasper Ridge,” Bio. 115, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Wildlife problems (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Binder: Docent Handbook.
    - Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve Stanford University. Includes sections on tours, trails, geology, plants, animals, ecology, research, etc. [circa 1982] (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Records, Accession ARCH-1997-199
  *collection needs work*
  - SU Radios, 1997-91 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Equipment, given away (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lists, 1985-90, of tours given, docents, SCVAS, checks deposited (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - SU seminars, 1988 – syllabuses, letters (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Centennial Weekend, 1990-91 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - New Roses Gallery Show (included JR images), 1975 – advertisement, mailing list, Herb Dengler's write-up for the event (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Comfort slide show, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Stanford Magazine article, 1975 – drafts and correspondence (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - JR dinner, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Public education statement, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - San Francisco Fdn., expenditure statements, 1979-82 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - San Francisco Fdn., financial reports (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - San Francisco Fdn., information (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - San Francisco Fdn., facility changes (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - C. L. fence, 1974-75 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fence removal, invoices, 1991-93 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Fencing cost, roat costs, 1973-88 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Animal fencing (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Chain link specs, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Locks and keys, 1973-85 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Security hardware, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Signs, layouts and estimates, 1979-80 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Security finances, 1977-78 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Catalogs from Oakland Fence Co., Cyclone Fence, and Page (Box 1, Folder [24])
  - Lawrence G. Brian and Co. Specifications and Contract documents (Box 1, Folder [25])
  - Market rents for Searsville housing, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Deferred maintenance, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - General building information (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Roofing information (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Cheap buildings – info on cheap storage buildings (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Bunkhouse, scheduling, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Paint all buildings – expenditure statements, project funding authorization, proposals, 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - AMES, proposal for project, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - USGS (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - NASA (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - USDA (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - SRI (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - UC Ag. Extension (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Los Altos Hunt, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Hiking, 1965-73 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Westridge fence adjustment, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Low-flow crossing and weather station, correspondence, 1970-72 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Westridge fence, 1968-70 – letters and legal documents regarding Rachel H. Fairweather Fund, letters regarding JR Fencing Proposal and JR Improvement, and letters about future plans for use of JR (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Westridge fence, letters and estimates, March 1970 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Ladera Dam, reports, letters, articles, and other materials, 1961-62 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Stanford Outdoor Primate Facility, letters, papers, article, 1969-81 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Cattle, 1958-80 – letters from Paul Ehrlich regarding cattle in serpentine, map of fence, and miscellaneous letters (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Sale of SLAC spoils, 1983-85 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Grazed grassland preserve, 1975-77 – letters re grazing in the SLAC corridor (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Shack Riders, 1960-74 – pamphlet, letters regarding proposed creek crossing, horse trail maps, letters re new shack site (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Grant support non-possibilities (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - State of California – EPA fund proposal (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - TNC alternative to TIE inventory, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
General note
1 file added to SC restricted files: Confidential materials on Page Kennedy wedding; George Pegelow employment